Guide to the Musicians’ Association of Seattle, American Federation of Musicians Local 76-493 Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Musicians’ Association of Seattle, American Federation of Musicians Local 76-493 records
1890-2010
1960-1990
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
5685
5685-001
Musicians' Association of Seattle
5.91 cubic feet 6 boxes
Records of Musicians’ Association of Seattle, American Federation of Musicians (AFM) Local 76-493; AFM Local 76; AFM Local 493; AFM Local 117; AFM Local 184; AFM Local 124; AFM Local 236; AFM Local 451; and AFM Local 461
The Musicians’ Association of Seattle, American Federation of Musicians Local 76-493 is a labor union that represents musicians in Seattle; Vashon Island; Clallam, Grays Harbor, Jefferson, King, Kitsap, Kittitas, Mason, Island, Pierce, San Juan, Skagit, Thurston, and Whatcom counties; and parts of Pacific County. Local 76-493 has been a labor organization since 1890 and is led by elected officers and an elected board of directors.
Musicians’ unions began in Seattle in 1890 with the creation of the Seattle chapter of the Musicians Mutual Protective Union (MMPU) Local 76. MMPU Local 76 reorganized under the American Federation of Musicians (AFM) Local 76 in 1898 and represented white musicians. Non-white musicians were barred from joining AFM Local 76 so they formed a separate union, AFM Local 458. Tension between the two unions resulted in the international union revoking Local 458’s charter in April of 1924. However, Black and other musicians of color were able to charter a replacement union, Local 493, later that year. In 1958, Local 76 and Local 493 were amalgamated into Local 76, ending the racial segregation of musicians’ unions in Seattle. In 1994 the local’s name was changed to Local 76-493.
Previously distinct AFM locals in Western Washington became amalgamated under the jurisdiction of Local 76-493 between 1980 and 2010 including AFM Local 117, Tacoma; AFM Local 184, Everett; AFM Local 124, Olympia; AFM Local 236, Aberdeen; AFM Local 451, Bellingham; and AFM Local 461, Mount Baker/Anacortes.
Sources:
Blecha, Peter. "AFM Local 493, Seattle's 'Negro Musicians' Union,' Holds Big Benefit Bash on May 29, 1951," February 20, 2013. http://www.historylink.org/File/10330.
Musicians’ Association of Seattle, American Federation of Musicians Local 76-493. "About Us." Musicians' Association of Seattle, February 28, 2017. https://local76-493.org/about-us/.
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
SERIES 1: MUSICIANS' ASSOCIATION OF SEATTLE, AFM LOCAL 76-493; AFM LOCAL 76, SEATTLE; AND AFM LOCAL 493, SEATTLE RECORDS, 1890-1891, 1919-1990
SERIES 2: AFM LOCAL 117, TACOMA, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1941-1996, undated
SERIES 3: AFM LOCAL 184, EVERETT, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1902-1991
SERIES 4: AFM LOCAL 124, OLYMPIA, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1941-1983
SERIES 5: AFM LOCAL 236, ABERDEEN, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1993-1994
SERIES 6: AFM LOCAL 451, BELLINGHAM, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1950-1981
SERIES 7: AFM LOCAL 461, MOUNT BAKER/ANACORTES, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1992-2010
Materials include meeting minutes, financial records, bylaws, bylaws amendments, resolutions, reports, correspondence, membership applications, attendance lists, essays, and newsletters documenting the activities of the Musicians’ Association of Seattle, American Federation of Musicians (AFM) Local 76-493, AFM Local 76, and AFM Local 493 in Seattle, Washington; AFM Local 117 in Tacoma, Washington; and AFM Local 184 and Snohomish County Musicians Club in Everett, Washington. Also included to a lesser extent are materials relating to the activities of AFM Local 124 in Olympia, Washington; AFM Local 236 in Aberdeen, Washington; AFM Local 451 in Bellingham, Washington; and AFM Local 461 in Mount Baker/Anacortes, Washington.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
Open to all users, but access to portions of the collection is restricted. Contact Special Collections for details.
Donated by Motter Snell, President of the Musicians’ Association of Seattle, 2012 February 10.
Musicians' Association of Seattle$vArchives; American Federation of Musicians.$bUnion Local 493 (Seattle, Wash.)$vArchives; American Federation of Musicians.$bUnion Local 493 (Seattle, Wash.); Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Musicians$xLabor unions$zWashington (State); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Music; Washington (State); Seattle
- MUSICIANS’ ASSOCIATION OF SEATTLE, AFM LOCAL 76-493; AFM LOCAL 76, SEATTLE; AND AFM LOCAL 493, SEATTLE RECORDS, 1890-1891, 1919-1990; SERIES 1; 0.46 cubic feet (1 box, including 29 microfilm reels)
  Materials include board meeting minutes, financial records, and membership applications documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 76-493, American Federation of Musicians Local 76, and American Federation of Musicians Local 493 in Seattle, Washington.
  Some materials in this series are restricted due to the presence of personally identifiable information.
  - Board meeting minutes, 1890-1891, 1919-1977; 8 microfilm reels (Box-folder 6)
  - Financial records: quarterly dues payments, 1925-1953; 18 microfilm reels (Box-folder 6)
  - Membership cards and payment records, approximately 1971-1990; 2 microfilm reels (Box-folder 6)
    Restricted due to the presence of personally identifiable information.
  - New member applications and transfer applications, 1977-1978; 1 microfilm reel (Box-folder 6)
- AFM LOCAL 117, TACOMA, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1941-1996, undated; SERIES 2; 1.51 cubic feet (1 box and 1 shared box)
  Materials include Executive Board meeting minutes, bylaws, correspondence, financial records, and reports documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 117 in Tacoma, Washington.
  - Executive Board minutes, 1941-1993 (Box-folder 1/1-32)
  - Bylaws and bylaws revisions, 1990, undated (Box-folder 1/32-33)
  - Correspondence regarding internal financial audits, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 1/35)
  - Per capita dues reports, initiation fee reports, union officer records, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 1/36)
  - Financial register of daily receipts and disbursements, 1958-1968 (Box-folder 1/37-47)
  - Check register, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 1/48-51)
  - Monthly transaction and balance sheets, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 2/1-8)
  - Financial records including tax reports and tax forms, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Labor organization annual reports, non profit corporation annual reports, and Pierce County Assessor affidavit, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Membership initiation fee reports, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 2/11)
- AFM LOCAL 184, EVERETT, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1902-1991; 1960-1991; SERIES 3; 3.74 cubic feet (2 boxes and 1 shared box)
  Materials include meeting minutes, correspondence, financial records, reports, and newsletters documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 184 in Everett, Washington. Also included are articles of incorporation, bylaws, meeting minutes, and financial records of the Snohomish County Musicians Club.
  - Quarterly payroll reports, tax forms, and budget notes, 1972-1983 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Correspondence with IRS, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Meeting minutes books, 1902-1983; 8 items (Box-folder 3)
  - Snohomish County Musicians Club meeting minutes book, 1966 (Box-folder 3)
  - Cash receipts ledgers, 1955-1968; 2 items (Box-folder 3)
  - Correspondence with IRS regarding tax return discrepancies and tax return forms, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Correspondence with IRS regarding tax return discrepancies, tax return forms, and correspondence with Washington State Employment Security Office, 1990 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Meeting minutes and newsletters, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Snohomish County Musicians Club articles of incorporation and bylaws, 1966-1977 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Snohomish County Musicians Club meeting minutes, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Appraisal of union building, 30621 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Newsletters, 1965-1986 (Box-folder 4/7-10)
  - Check registers, 1960-1984 (Box-folder 4/11-23)
  - Snohomish County Musicians Club check register, 1966-1986 (Box-folder 4/24)
  - Financial records, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 4/25)
  - Financial records, 1967-1988 (Box-folder 5/1-18)
- AFM LOCAL 124, OLYMPIA, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1941-1983; SERIES 4; 0.1 cubic feet (3 files)
  Materials include meeting minutes, bylaws amendments, and financial records documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 124 in Olympia, Washington.
  - Meeting minutes and bylaws amendments, 1941-1968 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Quarterly tax forms, 1977-1983 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Income and expense reports, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 2/14)
- AFM LOCAL 236, ABERDEEN, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1993-1994; SERIES 5; 0.1 cubic feet (1 file)
  Materials include notes and a resolution documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 236 in Aberdeen, Washington.
  - Notes and resolution regarding merger with AFM Local 76, Seattle, Washington, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 2/15)
- AFM LOCAL 451, BELLINGHAM, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1950-1981; SERIES 6; 0.1 cubic feet (4 files)
  Materials include meeting minutes, correspondence, attendance lists, and essays documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 451 in Bellingham.
  - Meeting minutes, 1962-1981 (Box-folder 4/26-27)
  - Roll call list for officers and guest lists from meetings, 1964-1972 (Box-folder 4/28)
  - Essay about AFM local 451 history, meeting notes, and correspondence, 1950-1969 (Box-folder 4/34)
- AFM LOCAL 461, MOUNT BAKER/ANACORTES, WASHINGTON RECORDS, 1992-2010; SERIES 7; 0.2 cubic feet (5 files)
  Materials include meeting minutes, financial records, correspondence, and attendance lists documenting the activities of the American Federation of Musicians Local 461 in Mount Baker/Anacortes, Washington.
  - Financial reports, 2000-2010 (Box-folder 4/29)
  - Correspondence and roster, 2004-2010 (Box-folder 4/30)
  - Meeting minutes, 1992-2010 (Box-folder 4/31-33)